LUIS JAVIER JIMÉNEZ NAVARRO

Itagüí, Antioquia. Colombia. Phone number: +57.312.854.4138. e-Mail: luisjavierjn@gmail.com

Keywords: Java, Spring, Junit, TDD, C/C++, SQL, BackEnd, Scrum, Jira, GIT, Docker, Intellij, Sonar, Teamwork, Finance

Cloud Experience: AWS EC2, AWS S3, Kubernetes Configuration, GitLab, Eureka Discovery, Spring Cloud, Spring WebFlux, Azure Cognitive Service and Text Analytics, Hexagonal Architecture.

I see myself as a responsible and proactive person who thinks that well done is better than well said. During my career I have worked with several technologies like C/C++, OpenGL Library 1.2, .NET Framework with C# as the programming language, Unity4, PHP, NodeJS, Angular4, React/Redux, Phaser Library, PL/SQL, Transact-SQL, and in the last few years I have become strong as a Java Developer using Spring Framework.

I actively use Git and more specifically Stash which integrates with other Atlassian software like Jira and Confluence. Also, for continuous integration I have been using Gitlab CI/CD and Kubernetes, taking care of the coverage and good practices with Sonar. I am determined, so I try again, I fail again, and I fail better until I reach the goal, and I do it fast. I understand that there are no shortcuts to any place worth going, so I keep myself up to date on what I need for the journey.

I am a finance enthusiast always looking at any kind of data chart related to prices, inflation, etc. Last but not least, my wife and daughter are my life, so I want them to be part of any decision or path that I take.

Education:

Aug 2008 ALEJANDRO DE HUMBOLDT UNIVERSITY (UAH)

Caracas, Venezuela

Graduate Diploma in Education Component.

This academic program prepares experts to a higher new level of competition, to demonstrate strengths in the theory, practice, usage and application of methodologies, techniques and procedures to produce learning to ensure a high level of efficiency by providing tools for the design, implementation and evaluation of educational management models, based on the new educational paradigms.

Nov 2004

INSTITUTE OF SUPERIOR STUDIES IN ADMINISTRATION (IESA) Master's Degree in Finance (MF). Caracas, Venezuela

IESA's Master's degree in Finance is a highly specialized program in that field which enables students to delve deeper into aspects of the financial realm to successfully perform in financial institutions, investment banking and the areas of financial management, risk, hedging and corporate finance.

- Credit Gran Mariscal de Ayacucho Foundation
- Specialization courses completed: Real Options, Finance for Entrepreneurs, Corporate Finance in Emerging Markets, International Economy.

Mar 2002

SIMÓN BOLIVAR UNIVERSITY (USB)

___Caracas, Venezuela

Software Engineer.

Computer Engineering deals with the nature and characteristics of the information, structure and classification, storage and retrieval and the various processes which can be automated. It is also interested in the properties of physical machines that perform these operations to produce systems for the efficient data processing.

• Specialization courses completed: Telecommunication Systems, Software Engineering, Computer Graphics, Computer Networks and Artificial Intelligence Topics "Robotic".

Experience:

<u>Jun 2022 – Feb 2024</u> FSB Technology (100% Remote)_

_Medellín, Colombia

Senior Java Developer.

- Managed changes to Registration Form & Account Details on the Backend side with PostgreSQL.
- Tested and troubleshooted casino games from the providers Scientific Games and Evolution Games.
- Configured GeoComply and IDComply to check geolocation and authorization for compliance.
- Production release of the website fitzdares.ca and on-call activities as part of the Bootcamp Team.

Apr 2021 – Jun 2022 **EPAM (100% Remote)**

_Medellín, Colombia

Senior Software Engineer. (+57.4.366.8113)

- Developed requirements for the project PCWS "Price Change Web Service" from Nordstrom.
- Changed configuration of a Spring Boot application to use yaml files instead of property files.

- Checked logs in CI/CD standard pipeline from GitLab and migrated Docker images from Gitlab repository to Artifactory.
- Changed libsonnet files to yml files for Kubernetes configuration. Scaled in/out Kubernetes resources.
- Coded PoC microservices for reading from and writing to Kafka topics.
- Coded a multithreaded audit program for validating data coming from several REST service endpoints, troubleshooting deadlock issues, and writing concurrency.
- Checked logs in Splunk and analyzed charts in New Relic as part of the On-Call tasks.
- Refactored tasks coded in Python for the Airflow system and checked logs as part of the On-Call responsibility.

<u>Sep 2019 – Sep 2020</u> **SMARTMATIC**

Medellín, Colombia

Java Senior Developer. (+507.831.25.00)

- Developed requirements on electoral systems for the countries: United States and Uganda. Programmed in Java 6, 7 or 8 with Spring Boot according to the assigned module, connecting to Oracle and SQLite databases. FrontEnd in AngularJS. All the systems had been dockerized completely, the database had its own Docker image, the same with the Java BackEnd, and the FrontEnd was compiled with npm thanks to a call from a Maven file, so the javascript files ended up within the Java WAR file.
- Created a Microservice using Spring Boot for the Platform project within the framework of hexagonal architecture which had across functionality to all the organization's projects. Transformed a monolithic program into microservices by using the Strangler Pattern and Domain Driven Design.
- Used Intellij as the programming IDE, from which debugging to the WAR file could be done directly inside the Docker container, rapid deployments using the plugins JRebel and Maven Helper, quality check with SonarLint, refinement of test units with JUnit and dependencies downloading from artifactory through a VPN connection to the company.
- Edited FrontEnd code utilizing the Google Chrome Developer Tools, Intellij and running the npm command apart so the FrontEnd executed from an independent port for fast changes. Coded change controls for the Oracle database through XML files, these change controls are taken after Jenkins execution, while changes during the development process are made through SQLDeveloper straight to the local database. Handled DB Browser for SQLite.
- Version control with GIT, complying with the process of Merge Request and subsequent Code Review
 for getting the approval of the code changes. Used Docker in Windows with Linux instances and
 handled Cygwin64 and Git Bash consoles.
- Handled Jira platform for documentation and control of user stories, I was part of a team made up of a
 Technical Leader, a Scrum Master, Developers and Testers, complying with the ceremonies: Daily,
 Planning, Review, Grooming and Retrospective for every two weeks Sprint. Used the collaboration tool
 Microsoft Teams and corporate email Microsoft Outlook for Business.
- Attended an induction and training in the Smartmatic's headquarters in Ciudad de Panamá, Panamá.

Nov 2017 – Aug 2019 **GLOBANT**

Medellín, Colombia

Java Developer. (+57.01800.952.06.41)

- Developed user stories related to the Southwest Airlines client account, utilizing Java 8 with Spring Boot and Oracle database, FrontEnd in Angular7 and React/Redux calling RESTful services from Java. Compiled FrontEnd with npm thanks to a call from a Gradle file.
- Used Intellij as the programming IDE for BackEnd, Visual Studio Code for FrontEnd and SQLDeveloper for connecting to the database. Handled tools for continuous integration, working with builds in Jenkins and delivering these builds to Develop and QA environments through Rundeck. Checked quality and technical debt using a Sonar server.
- Created and refined unit tests with JUnit and Mockito within the framework of TDD. Created behavioral tests for the Happy Path, using JBehave and Cucumber within the framework of BDD.
- Handled Atlassian suite: Jira for documentation and control of the user stories, Confluence for
 collaboration and control of projects, and Stash as GIT repository complying with the process of Pull
 Request and subsequent Code Review for getting a minimum of 3 approvals to proceed with the merge
 of the code changes into the main branch.
- Member of a team of 14 people: Technical Leader, Scrum Master, 2 Business Analysts, 8 Developers and 2 Testers. The Product Owner came from the client and worked with the Business Analysts.
- Attended the ceremonies: Daily, Planning, Review, Grooming and Retrospective for every two weeks Sprint. Used Scrum poker for assigning points to the user stories and used the refinement methodology called 3 amigos before Planning. Used Zoom for videoconference.
- Attended twice an *In situ* outsourcing and training in the Southwest Airlines headquarters in Dallas, Texas.
- Developed user stories related to the Royal Caribbean client account, adding and modifying rules for Apigee, sending data to Kafka using the Akka Actors model and executing the kubectl command for

monitoring Pods in Kubernetes and check logs to debug the application. Created a proof of concept on minikube for a legacy Java application for later migration to the main system architecture.

Mar 2016 – Oct 2017 TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES

Medellín, Colombia

Senior Developer. (+57.4.444.0348)

- Managed technologies related to the Banistmo project. Developed queries and stored procedures in Microsoft SQL Server 2008 R2, developed requirements in Java 6, deployed applications in IBM Websphere Application Server 8.5 using object promotion through the Harvest program.
- Developed an application formed by several CRUDs and was built up of RESTful services in Java 8, Front-End in Angular2, dependencies management with Maven and deployment in Apache Tomcat Server.

Sep 2015 – Feb 2016 **SOFTWARE ESTRATÉG**ICO

Medellín, Colombia

Outsourced Developer. (+57.4.520.8240)

- Programmed in Java 6 for the execution of tasks using the Quartz library and made Nginx setup as a
 reverse proxy for Apache, into the context of the projects PILA and Pago de Cesantías. Company:
 Enlace Operativo y Compuredes.
- Prepared reports using JavaServer Faces and Spring Web Flow. Company: Quipux.

Mar 2014 – Ene 2015 CASTILLOMAX OIL AND GAS

Caracas, Venezuela

Lead Programmer. (+58.212.762.7214)

- Coordinated programming tasks of the OPTIMAX 3D Project, a real-time 3D simulator of marine terminals for oil and cargo clearance. Managed a multidisciplinary team of 7 people including engineers and programmers. The software was presented at the World Petroleum Congress in Russia and the Latin American Petroleum Show in Maracaibo, Venezuela LAPS 2014.
- The software was built up with Unity 3D, C# programming language. Modelling of 3D objects was made in Maya and 3ds Max. It was used devices like Leap Motion Controller and Virtual reality Glasses.

Feb 2012 – Sep 2013 ECRS CORPORATION

Caracas, Venezuela

Project Engineer. (+58.212.481.9721 ext. 107)

- Implemented Driver on C++ for the fiscal printer QPrint MF. Created demo programs on C++, VB6, Java and C# (.Net) for using them at the Software Companies on integrations tasks with the fiscal printer driver.
- Developed system manuals and user manuals of the Driver OPrint MF and the example programs.
- Managed backup tasks with Norton Ghost 15.
- Managed the Company's Website developed with PHP5 and MySQL.

Jan 2007 – Ago 2011 **CLEVER FINANCIAL**

Caracas, Venezuela

Investment's System Manager. (+58.212.740.0390)

- Analysis, implementation and control of the investment systems which allowed to register the traded financial assets such as bonds, CD, stocks, as well as the buy & sell operations made by each client.
- Updated the portfolios current value on the database through Bloomberg API, managed reporting and automatization of backup operations. Tools and technologies: SQL Server 2008, VS.NET C# 2008, Matlab 7, Bloomberg API, iTextSharp, AJAX.
- Managed a team of 2 IT people.

Oct 2004 – Feb 2006 **PRICEWATERHOUSE COOPER**

Caracas, Venezuela

Software Engineer. (+58.212.700.6308)

- Developed a Workflow System which managed the documents approvals through different levels of the corporate hierarchy, which also allowed the parametrization of events, routes, rules, roles, roles groups and politics, each one being part of the document process management. Tools and technologies: SQL Server 2000, VS.NET C# 2003, Web Services, Windows Services, XML, Microsoft Message Queuing (MSMQ).
- Provided support on VB6 programs, Excel macros; installation of SAP Gui and Oracle Financial front end.

Mar 2003 – Jun 2004 ______Caracas, Venezuela

Independent Consultant.

• Developed Web forms in ASP.NET with C# and Oracle 9i database, supporting the Managers Evaluation Program conducted by the Institute of Superior Studies in Administration "IESA".

- Developed Web forms in JSP for the petition of treatments through the Oncological Program carried out by the Information Technology Office of the Ministry of Health. Also, created and designed the corresponding database on PostgresSQL 7.2.
- Designed and developed a database in Access 2000 to register the historical experience obtained by "Ingeniería Caura" Consultants, also created the interface formularies in order to produce reports in Word 2000 using Visual Basic for Applications.
- Configured the database to be used in the ERP program SCAV 2.5 of Archicentro in Orange Institute, and interacted with different departments or agencies of the Orange Institute to give assistance and training on the usage of this tool.

Jul 2001 - Dec 2002 PDVSA INTEVEP EXPLORATION AND PRODUCTION MANAGEMENT Caracas, Venezuela

Feb 2002 – Dec 2002 Programmer Analyst / Fundation for Research and Development of the USB. (+58.212.906.3920)

- Designed object oriented graphic libraries 2D and 3D in OpenGL and C++ language.
- Designed and developed VRJuggler applications, for the visualization of reservoirs structures on immersive displays (CAVE, Walls) and workstations.
- Integrated different modules (libraries) developed in different languages: C, C++, Java and Fortran using JNI.
- Wrote technical documentation under UML notation in a development process of RUP Methodology.
- Migrated code for different operating systems, specifically: Windows 2000, IRIX and Solaris.
- Attended VRJuggler programming course in Glass House Studio. Marshalltown, Iowa. EEUU.

Jul 2001 – Dec 2001 Intern (Departament of Modelling and Simulation of Reservoirs).

• Designed and developed a system for oil fields visualization using OpenGL, Java, C++ for Windows, Solaris and Irix operating systems.

Jul 1999 – Sep 1999 INSTITUTE OF SUPERIOR STUDIES IN ADMINISTRATION (IESA) Caracas, Venezuela

Short-term internship.

• Upgraded the handling of activities on a control system for the Institute's Help Desk, developed SQL queries along with an interface on the intranet system using ASP and JDBC connection.

Extra:

Place and date of birth: Caracas, Venezuela. January 25th, 1979.

Marital status: Married.

Spanish - Native.

English - Working Proficiency.

Courses and Events.

- Vacations. Miami-Orlando. March 2022. 14 days.
- Training in Smartmatic headquarters. Ciudad de Panamá. Panamá. Noviembre 2019. 2 semanas.
- Outsourcing in Southwest Airlines. Dallas, Texas. November 2018. 2 weeks.
- Outsourcing in Southwest Airlines. Dallas, Texas. June 2018. 2 weeks.
- Vacations. New York City. June 2017. 10 days.
- Project Monitoring and Control using Earned Value. December 2014. 16 hours.
- XXIV Latin American Petroleum Show LAPS 2014. Maracaibo. Julio 1-3, 2014.
- Economic Outlook Forum 2014, Ecoanalítica. Quinta La Esmeralda, Caracas. November 7, 2013.
- Forum Investment Opportunities and Prospects about the Public Stock Exchange Bicentennial 2012. Public Stock Exchange Bicentennial. December 7, 2011.
- Money Laundering Prevention, Firm: Araque, Reyna, Sosa, Viso & Pittier. Marzo 2009. 2 horas.
- How to move your company to the e-Commerce. Venezuelan Chamber of Electronic Commerce "Cavecom-e". July 2008 1 days.
- Doing Business with USA. Firm: Roth Rousso Katsman & Schneider, LLP Nov 2005. 1 day.
- Business Workshop Initiation of Banco Provincial. March 2005. 8 hours.

- Forum Business Management: Value and Strategy, UCAB 2004.
- VRJuggler Programming. Marshalltown, Iowa. EEUU 2002. 4 days.
- SIGGRAPH 2001 Conference. Los Angeles, California. EEUU 2001. 1 week.
- Work Team Formation for Software Development. USB 2001. 28 hours.
- Analyst Programmer. American Academy. 1 year. 1995.

Udemy Courses Certified

- Learn Docker from Scratch to Swarm and Kubernetes.
- Introducing Spring Boot.
- AngularJS For Beginners.
- Spring Boot. Complete guide from development to deployment.
- Principles of Neurolinguistic Programming and Coaching.
- MongoDB for Java Developers Project Based.
- Quick introduction to influxdb.